A Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 1881-1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1902 October 31, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter and thanks him for his kind words regarding Dabney's visit to Princeton. Wilson comments on the selection of a new president for the University of Virginia and says that because of his affection for the University, he would only suggest the very best man for the job. Wilson says that he does not know of any such man at this time, but will write Dabney should someone come to mind for the position. The letter ends with regards from Wilson and his wife to Dabney and Mrs. Dabney. The closing is typed "Faithfully yours," and signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "13 Oct 1902" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1902 November 10, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that the presidency of the University of Virginia has been offered to him three times. He never gave any indication that he would accept the position. Wilson says that Dabney is at perfect liberty to state the "whole case" to anyone. Wilson says that he was unaware of any opposition to him as president, just opposition to having any president at all, but that if they must have a president, the "opposition" would agree to Wilson. Wilson writes that he still does not know of anyone that he could strongly recommend for the position. The letter closes with regret that Dabney has been distressed by a "cock and bull" story. The typed closing reads "Cordially and Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1910 April 19, TLS 4 p. (Box 1)
  Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes of his receipt of a recommendation for a professor to be hired at Princeton and promises to forward the letter to the appropriate person. Wilson then says that he is very much "disinclined" to go into politics, but the situation there makes it difficult not to do so. Wilson writes that he would like to see Dabney, and that being with Dabney makes Wilson feel like a boy again. The typed closing reads "affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 November 16, ALS 4 p. with envelope (negative photostat) (Box 1)
  Wilson, Staunton, Virginia, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he and Dabney did not have a chance to talk about the initiative, referendum and recall when they were together so Wilson says it would be worthwhile for him to "summarize" it somewhat more formally. The remainder of the letter is Wilson's summarization. The closing reads "Faithfully Yours, Woodrow Wilson. On the photostat of the envelope, there is a note in Dabney's hand that reads "16 Nov., 1911 I had this letter published with the extended comments of my own, in the [Richmond] Times Dispatch, and it was reprinted in many other paper. Reprints of it were also distributed from the Woodrow Wilson Headquarters in New York!"
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 November 4, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson apologizes for not having told Dabney of his travel plans. Wilson has received Dabney's request to publish his letter and gives his approval. Wilson says that if Dabney thinks the letter needs to be put in a better form, to let him know and Wilson will put it in "shape." The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 December 11, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, in Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson responds to Dabney's letter of the sixth. The letter includes a sentence Dabney suggests adding to Wilson's "Staunton" letter before it is published. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 December 18, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter sent on December 14. Wilson mentions a controversy between him and "Proctor of Cincinnati" regarding the Graduate College in Princeton. The typed closing reads "Always affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 December 22, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), in Trenton, New Jersey to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his help in the publication of his letter. Wilson also mentions the editorial by Mr. [John Stewart] Bryan in the [Richmond] Times Dispatch. The typed closing reads "Affectionately and gratefully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1911 December 27, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of December 21 and thanks Dabney for what he is doing and the "value of what you are telling me from time to time." Wilson mentions making a series of speeches in Virginia, and suggests that Dabney is in a better position to judge if the Virginia legislature should invite him to do so. Wilson says that the letter Dabney amended has been well received by Wilson's New York headquarters. The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 January 5, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letters and their enclosures. Wilson mentions that he has received an answer to a letter from Archie Patterson. Wilson says that he is willing to come to Richmond to speak after February. The typed closing reads "Always faithfully yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 January 11, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of the sixth. He mentions friends of [William Jennings] Bryan and how [Robert M.] LaFollette is regarded. Wilson says that it is unjust to "indulge in flings at either of those men." Wilson describes this as dropping a hint to Dabney. Wilson describes the process of the campaign as interesting and promising. The typed closing read "Faithfully and affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 January 16, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson mentions a suggestion he gave to Dabney and the results thereof. Wilson also thanks Dabney for polling Virginia's congressmen. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 January 25, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson apologizes to Dabney for not writing but explains that he knows Dabney will understand why. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letters. Wilson says that his days are "one continual absorbing rush." Wilson mentions the response in Virginia to the "Harvey-Watterson affair." Wilson ends the letter by saying he is surprised to hear that he has been invited to speak in Richmond, as Wilson says no such invitations have reached him. The typed closing reads "Faithfully and affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Ellen Axson Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 February 9, ALS 12 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Ellen Wilson, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson sends more details of the "Carnegie pension affair." Most of the letter describes who is eligible for the pension, and the requirements thereof. She writes concerning Woodrow Wilson's financial situations, his lack of income since leaving Princeton, and the costs he has incurred doing "public service." She says that she supposes he could take a "paying" job, but that would force him to give up his leadership in the reform movement. Mrs. Wilson writes that he only receives $1000 a year from his books, and that goes to pay for "life insurances." Mrs. Wilson writes that when Wilson applied for the Carnegie pension he had not been elected governor, and had no means of support. She trusts Dabney's discretion in the matter: "I don't know what he would do to me if he knew I was writing all this." The closing is "Yours very cordially," and the letter is signed "Ellen A. Wilson." The envelope has "From Mrs. Woodrow Wilson" and "Feb. 9 1912" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 February 27, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson extends his sympathy to Dabney over the loss of his daughter [Lucy Davis Dabney, who died of juvenile diabetes at age nine]. The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "1902 16 March" and "About Lucy" pencilled on.
- Ellen Axson Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 March 13, ALS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Ellen Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson requests a copy of her letter of 1912 February 9 regarding the pension issue. The closing reads "Yours very cordially, Ellen A. Wilson." The envelope has "From Mrs. Woodrow Wilson." and "March 13, 1912" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 March 20, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson discusses the issues of the "pension question" and agrees that is too late now to take up the matter. Wilson also mentions the difficult time Dabney is going through and Wilson is touched that Dabney should think of him during this time of "infinite pain and depression." The typed closing reads "Affectionately Yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 May 13, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson assures Dabney that he has not suffered a reported breakdown, only a severe cold. Wilson also expresses concerns that Dabney has had "nerve" trouble and has been unable to sleep. He says that he thinks Dabney's intention to go to the "other side of the water" to recuperate is a good idea. Wilson reports that things politically are in good shape. Wilson is disappointed in the small numbers of people who have voted in the primaries and he thinks the "purpose" to nominate him is as strong as ever. The letter ends with Wilson mentioning that he saw Dick Byrd and Mr. Byrd was hopeful that the "Virginia situation" would be controlled in Wilson's favor. The typed closing reads, "With genuine affection, Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 August 1, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Sea Girt, New Jersey, to Dabney in Paris, France. Wilson apologizes that he did not notice the change of address that Dabney gave in his last letter. Wilson fears that his last letter is "wandering" around Europe seeking Dabney. Wilson mentions that Dabney has had troubles and political disappointments in Virginia. Wilson also mentions that results in Baltimore should cheer Dabney. Wilson concludes that he has "piles" of letters and cannot write more then a few lines. The typed closing reads "Affectionately Yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Mrs. Richard Heath Dabney 1912 August 12, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Sea Girt, N.J. to Mrs. Dabney. Thanks her for her note of congratulations and begs her to pardon his delayed reply. Has gotten several notes from Heath but they did not include his European address so he couldn’t reply. Asks her to convey his love.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 August 13, TLS 4 p. with envelopes (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Paris (forwarded to Charlottesville, Virginia). Wilson explains that he has not written because he was not sure what address in Europe to use, but that he wrote Mrs. Dabney and received a correct address from her. Wilson is touched by Dabney's support for his nomination and that he often thinks of Dabney, even if he is unable to write. Wilson sends wishes that Dabney is getting refreshed and renewed. The typed closing reads "Always faithfully and affectionately yours'" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 September 6, TLS 2 p. with envelope. (Box 1)
  Wilson, Sea Girt, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson congratulates Dabney on the birth of his daughter, Alice Saunders Dabney. The typed closing reads "Always affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "About Alice's birth" pencilled on.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 October 21, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson is home for a few days until "Mr. Roosevelt is fighting for himself again." Wilson is delighted Dabney's daughter and wife are getting along so well. The typed closing reads "affectionately yours," and the letter is signed Woodrow Wilson.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 November 20, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Bermuda to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson tells Dabney that he would very much like to visit the University of Virginia when he comes to Staunton, but with as little ceremony as possible. Wilson says that he loves the University of Virginia for its "simplicities" and not for the trouble he has gotten into. Wilson says that he is settled in Bermuda for a little period and hopes to come back with new zest and refreshment. The typed closing on letter one reads "Faithfully yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." A second letter of the same date is about Dabney's letter regarding Randolph Harrison. Wilson ends by wishing Dabney were in Bermuda. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "Bermuda, Nov. 20 1912" noted on it.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 December 3, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Bermuda, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson says he understands perfectly Dabney's actions regarding office appointment recommendations. Wilson will only be able to spend a few hours in Charlottesville. He is struggling with masses of correspondence, even "down here." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "Bermuda Dec. 3 1912" written on it.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 December 12, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. The letter is regarding two names ([Paul B.?] Barringer and [Henry St. George?] Tucker) that Dabney recommended for consideration by Wilson. The typed closing reads, "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Mr. Tumulty, Secretary to the Governor of New Jersey, to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 December 21, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Letter from Wilson's secretary to Dabney regarding the nomination letters for Mr. Bryan and Mr. Townsend with reference to Mr. William Scott.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1912 December 23, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson writes that he is too busy to spend more than the exact amount of promised time in Staunton. Wilson will arrive at 8 o'clock in the evening. He asks Dabney to be "on hand" in Staunton. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Mr. and Mrs. Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney Undated [1912 December?], Western Union Telegram with envelope (Box 1)
  The Wilsons regret that they cannot stop in Charlottesville and send Christmas greetings.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 January 7, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for sending Tucker's letter. Wilson mentions a business failure connected with him at the Jamestown Exposition. Wilson adds that it was a joy to see Dabney. Wilson mentions Dabney's nose "trouble" and says that he thought Dabney did not look well. Wilson says the trip to Staunton did him no harm, but he came back feeling better that when he started. Wilson says that there had been some suggestion, perhaps in the [Richmond] Times-Dispatch, that it was not in "good taste" to give a talk to the machine men in Virginia. Wilson hopes this is not the general impression. Wilson writes that his friends will have to get used to his way of always having a dart for somebody. Wilson writes that his passage was on the spur of the moment. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 January 30, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson replies to Dabney's letter of the 26th. Wilson writes that the papers enclosed with Dabney's letter will receive his careful attention. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 February 3, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the information he sent from Seattle. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 February 20, TLS 2 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery), Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the information he sent regarding Bernard Mann. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 March 12, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of the ninth and says that he has only time enough to send Dabney "only this line with my love." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 March 14, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson refers to recommendations Dabney has made regarding a Postmaster appointment. Wilson also mentions a recommendation Dabney has made for the position of Naval Officer for the Port of New Orleans. The typed closing reads "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 March 21, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's recommendation letter of March 20. The typed closing reads "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." There is an autograph note at the bottom that reads "Dear Heath, This is a 'form letter' It should have ended Yours affectionately, W.W."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 March 25, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson says a statement regarding lawyers was exaggerated and goes on to discuss lawyers and their connections to corporations. Wilson ends by saying that all of Dabney's letters are welcome. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours", and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 April 3, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson responds to Dabney's recommendation of Mr. Williams. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." There is an autograph note that reads "I'm afraid I'm committed to another man W.W." There is a red "UVa Library" stamp beneath the signature.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 May 29, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson comments on an article written about him by Dabney in Corks and Curls and expresses his gratitude for it. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 June 3, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for sending information on Mr. Watts and Mr. Davis. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 June 17, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for sending information on Dr. Eigenmann and Mr. de Saulles. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 June 25, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Maine. Wilson acknowledges receipt of information from Dabney regarding Mr. Lewis Aylett. Wilson hopes Mr. and Mrs. Dabney will have an enjoyable vacation. Wilson mentions that he, the First Lady, and their daughter will be leaving for their vacation home in Cornish and that he is looking forward to the vacation. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The letter has one autograph correction.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 July 14, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Maine. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of July 10 regarding Lewis Aylett. The President writes that he has just returned from Cornish and is refreshed and enjoyed being on the links. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 July 31, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Maine. Wilson is disappointed that he cannot appoint Louis Aylett as Richmond Postmaster but there are many things "one cannot do." The President writes that he is envious of Dabney being on vacation. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 September 5, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)